Guide to the Chase Kimball Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Chase Kimball papers
1906-1971
MS 313
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
28.75
(41 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, minutes, reports, organizational and financial records, speeches, topical files, notes, and printed literature documenting Chase Kimball's participation in some thirty-five national and local social, political, and religious organizations, primarily concerned with international peace and justice, and also with civic improvement in Connecticut and especially Waterbury. Since Kimball was active in or received literature from nearly all peace organizations between 1930 and 1939, the Kimball papers are a full record of the literature and ephemera produced and are a source of information on fund-raising and other organizing activities and on the tensions created in the peace movement by differences in intellectual approaches and organizing strategies. Extensive files exist for the American Friends Service Committee, the Connecticut Council on International Relations, the Connecticut Peace Conference, the Emergency Peace Campaign, the International Peace Campaign, the League of Nations Associations, the National Council for Prevention of War, the Waterbury Council for Peace Action, and the Young Men's Christian Association. Major correspondents include Devere Allen, Nathaniel Horton Batchelder, Clark Eichelberger, Lewis Fox, Paul Harris, Florence Kitchelt, Laura Puffer Morgan, Rachel Nason, Frederic Smedley, Horace Dutton Taft, and Wayne Womer.
Kimball, Chase, 1902-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Chase Kimball, 1946-1951; and Mary Eliza Kimball, Elmira Lee Kimball Byron, and Helen Chase Kimball-Brooke in 1990.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. Organizations, 1922-1946. II. Select Correspondence, 1925-1942. III. General Correspondence, 1923-1942. IV. Topical Files, 1920-1946.
Scope and Contents
The Chase Kimball Papers document Chase Kimball's participation in some twenty-five national and local, social, political, and religious organizations, and are an especially valuable source of information on the peace movement in America in the 1930s and on civic improvement in Waterbury, Connecticut. Because Kimball was personally involved in or collected literature from all peace organizations between 1930 and 1939, the Kimball Papers comprise an illuminating record of tensions in the peace movement caused by differences in intellectual approaches and organizing strategies.
The correspondence, Minutes, reports, organizational and financial records, speeches, printed ephemera, and topical files which compose the papers were given to the Yale University Library by Chase Kimball between 1946 and 1951. They are arranged in four series much as Kimball organized his files originally:
Series I, ORGANIZATIONS, is the largest series in the papers and contains the correspondence, organizational and financial records, minutes, reports, and printed matter that Kimball collected for each organization in which he participated. Most organizations represented in the series are in some way related to international justice or the peace movement of the 1930s, but a few files document Kimball's other voluntary activities on behalf of religious and civic groups in Waterbury and throughout Connecticut.
Kimball played a direct role in several of the peace organizations represented in the series. The most voluminous records are those for the League of Nations Association and its Connecticut affiliate. Since Kimball served as vice-president of the Connecticut chapter and as a member of the disarmament committee of the national association, the files, through minutes, correspondence, and reports, show the planning and administration of various organizing and educational campaigns and projects. Similarly, since Kimball served as treasurer of the Connecticut Council on International Relations and as a member of the International Relations Committee of the Connecticut Council of Churches, there are files documenting the activities of these local organizations. The development and projects of the Waterbury Council for Peace Action are also well documented as are its ties to the Connecticut Peace Conference.
Kimball described himself as the chairman for peace of Connecticut's fifth congressional district and worked in this capacity with many other peace groups including the Emergency Peace Campaign, the National Council for Prevention of War, and, though he was not a pacificist or a Quaker, with the American Friends Service Committee. For these organizations there is much printed material as well as correspondence and project files. From other peace organizations, such as the International Peace Campaign and the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Kimball merely saved the printed material he received, but at least for the International Peace Campaign the files represent a rather complete rum of printed material.
The ORGANIZATIONS series also documents Kimball's work in other civic and religious groups. The files for the Connecticut Merit System Association and the National Civil Service Reform League reflect Kimball's interest in the "good government" movement. There are also extensive files for Kimball's work with the Young Men's Christian Association and in the Congregational Church.
Series II, SELECT CORRESPONDENCE, is composed of Kimball's correspondence with leaders in the peace movement, both nationally and in Connecticut, and with some Connecticut political figures with whom Kimball had substantive exchanges. Like Kimball many of these correspondents were active participants in more than one peace organization. Therefore, correspondence in this series includes discussions of more general concerns, while correspondence left in Series I concerns specifically the organization under which it is filed. The series includes some correspondence with the two most prominent women in the Connecticut peace campaign, Florence Kitchelt and Rachel Nason. The series also reflects the important role that volunteers and the organization of volunteers played in the peace movement.
Series III, GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, contains the routine correspondence that Kimball received and generated particularly in his peace movement and political organizing activities. The correspondence is composed of requests for literature, form letters, fund raising requests, and incidental items received from regional peace organizations outside Connecticut. Occasional letters to politicians are also filed here.
Series IV, TOPICAL FILES, contains background material in the form of correspondence, notes, lists, and printed material, mainly on subjects related to Kimball's peace work such as neutrality, economic sanctions, and the like. The largest amount of material in the series concerns the general organization of peace work and peace workers in Connecticut in different years for congressional campaigns and in various localities. The series also includes some material used by Kimball in preparation for his radio broadcasts and other speeches.
Biographical / Historical
Chase Kimball was born on January 20, 1902, in Waterbury, Connecticut. He was a lawyer and banker in Waterbury and was active in local and civic and peace organizations. Kimball graduated from Yale College in 1925 and received an LL.B. from the Yale Law School in 1928. He returned to Waterbury in 1931 to practice law and to take charge of the trust department of the Waterbury National Bank. An advocate of international peace and justice in the 1930s, Kimball served as vice-president of the Connecticut branch of the League of Nations Association, treasurer of the Connecticut Council on International Relations, and chairman for peace of the Fifth Congressional District of Connecticut. He participated both locally and nationally in a number of peace organizations. Kimball was also active in the Connecticut Council of Churches, the National Civil Service Reform League, the Y.M.C.A., and the Mission Council of Congregational Churches. Following World War II, he completed a Ph.D. at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy and taught international law at various universities. He married Mary Lee Evans in l942, and they had three children. Kimball died in Milton, Massachusetts, on June 4, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Congregationalists -- Connecticut; Internationalism; Law; Pacifism -- Societies, etc.; Peace -- Societies, etc.; Religion and international relations; Voluntarism; Women; Connecticut -- Politics and government; United States -- Foreign policy; United States -- Foreign relations; Waterbury (Conn.); Lawyers; Allen, Devere, 1891-1955; Batchelder, Nathaniel Horton; Eichelberger, Clark M. (Clark Mell), 1896-1980; Fox, Lewis; Goss, Edward W.; Haile, Pennington, 1902-1982; Harris, Paul; Kimball, Chase, 1902-; Kitchelt, Florence Ledyard Cross, 1874-1961; Koppleman, Herman Paul, 1880-; Morgan, Laura Puffer, 1874-1962; Nason, Rachel; Shotwell, James T., 1874-1965; Smedley, Frederic C.; Smith, J. Joseph; Taft, Horace Dutton, 1861-1943; Van Kirk, Walter W. (Walter William), 1891-1956; Walcott, Frederic Collin, 1869-1949; Womer, Wayne Wakefield; American Association for the United Nations; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; American Committee for Non-Participation in Japanese Aggression; American Friends Service Committee; Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies; Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education; Connecticut Council on International Relations; Connecticut Merit System Association; Connecticut Peace Conference; Emergency Peace Campaign (U.S.); Fight for Freedom, Inc; Foreign Policy Association; General Council of the Congregational and Christian Churches of the United States. Council for Social Action; International Peace Campaign; League of Nations Association of Connecticut; League of Nations Association (U.S.); League to Enforce Peace (U.S.); National Civil Service League; National Council for Prevention of War (U.S.); National Peace Conference (U.S.); Taft School; Waterbury Council for Peace Action; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; Worldover Press Service; YMCA (Waterbury, Conn.); YMCA. International Committee; Youth Movement for World Recovery
- ORGANIZATIONS, 1922-1946; Series I; 5.25 linear feet (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, organizational and financial records, minutes, reports, and printed material for organizations to which Kimball belonged. The material is organized by organization name and arranged in alphabetical order.
  - America First
    General note
    See: box 1, folders 7-9
  - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1933-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    See also: box 4, folders 30-31
  - American Committee for Non-Participation in Japanese Aggression, 1932-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1932-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Citizens for Victory
  - Citizens Good Government Association
  - Committee to Defend America
    - National, 1941-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
    - Connecticut and Waterbury chapters, 1941-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Connecticut Conference of Congregational and Christian Churches
    See: box 2, folder 19
  - Connecticut Council of Churches, 1933-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Connecticut Council on International Relations
    - General, 1931-1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
    - Bank books, receipts, financial statements, 1927-1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Round Table study groups, 1932-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      See also: box 3, folders 22-26
  - Connecticut Merit System Association, 1926, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association, 1940-1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Connecticut Peace Conference
    - General, 1936-1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 22-26)
    - Account books, receipts, financial statements, 1927-1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Lists re: enrollment and signature campaigns, 1938-1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Connecticut State Salvage Committee, 1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Council for Social Action
    - General, 1934-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
    - Social Action Committees in Connecticut and New England, 1935-1938, 1941-1942, n.d (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
  - Emergency Peace Campaign
    - General, 1936-1937, undated (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
    - Printed matter, lists, 1935-1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Federal Union, Inc., 1941-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Fight for Freedom, Inc., 1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    See also: box 1, folders 7-9
  - Foreign Policy Association, Inc.
    - General, 1930-1946 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Study outlines and other publications, 1930-1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Gaylord Farm Sanitorium, 1939, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - International Peace Campaign
    - General, 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Printed matter, 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 44-50)
  - League of Nations Association
    - General, 1929-1934 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - General, 1935-1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 52-56)
    - Advisory Committee on Disarmament, 1931-1933 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Board of Directors, 1936-1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 58-61)
    - Committee for Concerted Peace Efforts, 1937-1939, undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Printed matter, 1930-1942, undated (Box 7, Folder 63-67)
    - "Service Notebook", 1937-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 68-70)
  - League of Nations Association - Connecticut Branch
    - General, 1925, 1928-1933 April (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - General, 1933 May - 1940 (Box 8, Folder 72-80)
    - General, 1941-1942, undated (Box 9, Folder 81-82)
    - Hartford (First Congressional District), 1933-1936 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Printed matter, 1932-1942, undated (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Signature campaign, 1933-1935, undated (Box 9, Folder 85-87)
    - Speakers, 1934-1938, 1941, undated (Box 9, Folder 88)
      See also: box 19, folders 198-200
  - League of Nations Union, 1925, 1930-1942 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - League to Enforce Peace, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - National Civil Service Reform League
    - General, 1922, 1933-1937 (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Printed matter, 1922-1940, undated (Box 9, Folder 92)
      See also: box 2, folder 19
  - National Council for Prevention of War
    - General, 1927-1941, undated (Box 10, Folder 93-98)
    - Peace bond sales in Connecticut, 1935-1937, undated (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Peace bond publicity, 1935-1936, undated (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Printed matter, 1923, 1927, 1931-1941,undated (Box 10, Folder 101-103)
    - Printed matter, undated (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - Printed resolutions, 1927-1937 (Box 11, Folder 105-106)
      See also: box 13, folders 135-137
  - National Peace Conference
    - General, 1935-1941, undated (Box 11, Folder 107-109)
    - Printed matter, 1935-1939, undated (Box 11, Folder 110)
      See also: box 2, folders 14-16
  - Naugatuck Valley Association of Congregational, Churches, Social Relations Committee, 1935, undated (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Nofrontier News Service
    See: box 14, folder 138
  - Peace Action Service
    See: box 10, folders 93-98
    See: box 13, folders 135-137
  - Russian War Relief, Inc., 1941-1942, undated (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Russian War Relief, Waterbury Chapter, 1942, undated (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Taft School, Watertown, Conn., 1930-1941, undated (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Waterbury Council for Peace Action
    - General, 1934-1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - Minutes, 1934-1939 (Box 12, Folder 116)
  - Waterbury Society for Mental Hygiene, 1934-1937 (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - Waterbury Taxpayers' Association, Inc., 1933-1942, undated (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Waterbury Youth Peace Council: Model, Disarmament Conference, 1932-1933 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Wheat Dinner Committee, 1931-1932, 1936, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1933-1938, undated (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - World Federal Unionists, 1939-1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - World Over Press
  - World Peace Foundation, 1930-1937, undated (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - Young Men's Christian Association, Connecticut, 1927, 1934-1939, undated (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Young Men's Christian Association, International, Committee
    - General, 1931-1939 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Minutes, 1934-1937 (Box 12, Folder 126-127)
    - Minutes, 1939, 1942, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - Printed matter, 1933-1942, undated (Box 13, Folder 129)
  - Young Men's Christian Association, Waterbury, Conn.
    - General, 1930-1939, undated (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Board of Directors, 1930-1942 (Box 13, Folder 131-133)
    - Christian Education Policy, 1933-1936, undated (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Youth Movement for World Recovery, 1932-1939 (Box 13, Folder 135-137)
- SELECT CORRESPONDENCE, 1925-1942; Series II; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series is composed of Kimball's correspondence with associates in the peace movement and with some Connecticut political figures. The correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order. Extensive cross-references are provided to Series I since correspondence with these selected correspondents concerning organization matters has been left as Kimball filed it in the files for the organization.
  - Allen, Devere, 1933-1942 (Box 14, Folder 138)
  - Bakewell, Charles M., 1933-1934 (Box 14, Folder 139)
  - Batchelder, Nathaniel Horton, 1936-1940 (Box 14, Folder 140)
    See also: box 3, folders 22-28
  - Bingham, Hiram, 1925-1936, undated (Box 14, Folder 141)
  - Citron, William M., 1934-1938, undated (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - Danaher, John A., 1938-1942 (Box 14, Folder 143)
  - Eichelberger, Clark
  - Fox, Lewis, 1933-1937 (Box 14, Folder 144)
    See also: box 1, folder 6
    See also: box 9, folder 83
  - Goss, Edward W., 1931-1936 (Box 14, Folder 145)
  - Haile, Pennington
    See: box 7, folders 68-70
  - Harris, Paul
  - Kitchelt, Florence L.C., 1930-1940 (Box 14, Folder 146)
    See also: box 2, folders 14-18
  - Koppleman, Herman P., 1933-1942 (Box 14, Folder 147)
  - Lonergan, Augustine, 1932-1938 (Box 14, Folder 148)
  - Maciora, Lucien, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 149)
  - MacKnight, Jesse
  - Maloney, Francis T., 1934-1942 (Box 14, Folder 150-151)
  - Monkiewicz, Boleslaus J., 1938-1940 (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Morgan, Laura Puffer
    See: box 5, folders 51-56
  - Nason, Rachel, 1932-1937 (Box 15, Folder 153)
  - Nye, Gerald P., 1934-1941 (Box 15, Folder 154)
  - Pope, James P., 1936, undated (Box 15, Folder 155)
  - Searles, Ruth
  - Shotwell, James
    See: box 6, folders 58-61
  - Smedley, Frederic C., 1933-1934, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 156)
  - Smith, J. Joseph, 1934-1937,undated (Box 15, Folder 157-158)
  - Taft, Horace Dutton (Box 15, Folder 159)
    See also: box 2, folder 11
    See also: box 11, folder 114
  - Talbot, Joseph E., 1942 (Box 15, Folder 160)
  - Van Kirk, Walter
    See: box 11, folders 107-109
  - Walcott, Frederic C., 1930-1932, undated (Box 15, Folder 161)
  - Womer, Wayne Wakefield, 1937-1942 (Box 15, Folder 162)
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1946, undated; Series III; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Routine correspondence such as requests for literature, form letters, fund raising requests, and occasional items from other regional peace organizations comprise this series. The correspondence is arranged in rough chronological order.
  - 1923-1937 (Box 16, Folder 163-173)
  - 1938-1941, 1942 January-Sep, 1945-1946, undated (Box 17, Folder 174-184)
- TOPICAL FILES, 1920-1946; Series IV; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains correspondence, notes, printed material and other types of background material organized by topic, The topical files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Armistice Day celebration - general, 1920-1931 (Box 18, Folder 185)
  - Congress - background material, 1926-1932 (Box 18, Folder 186)
  - Disarmament general, 1926-1931 (Box 18, Folder 187)
  - Ethiopia, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 188)
  - Internationalism - post-World War II, 1945-1946 (Box 18, Folder 189)
  - Japan, economic sanctions against, 1935-1939 (Box 18, Folder 190-191)
  - National Recovery Administration and unemployment, 1938-1939 (Box 18, Folder 192)
  - Neutrality legislation, 1934-1939 (Box 18, Folder 193)
  - Peace work
    - General, 1936-1939 (Box 18, Folder 194)
    - Literature from miscellaneous organizations, 1925-1935 (Box 18, Folder 195)
    - Literature from miscellaneous organizations, 1935-1942 (Box 19, Folder 196)
    - Miscellaneous background material and notes, 1933-1937 (Box 19, Folder 197)
  - Peace work - Connecticut
    - Congressional election 1934, 1932-1934 (Box 19, Folder 198)
    - Congressional election 1936 (Box 19, Folder 199)
    - Congressional election 1940 (Box 19, Folder 200)
  - Peace work - Connecticut Fifth Congressional District
    - General, 1932-1937 (Box 19, Folder 201)
    - Potential speakers lists, 1934-1936 (Box 19, Folder 202)
    - Lists, 1932-1935, undated (Box 19, Folder 203-204)
    - Meriden, New Britain, 1934-1938 (Box 19, Folder 205)
    - Torrington, Harwinton, New Hartford, 1933-1938 (Box 19, Folder 206)
    - New Milford, Roxbury, Bridgewater, 1933-1937 (Box 19, Folder 207)
    - Derby, Ansonia, Seymour, Shelton, Oxford, 1933-1936 (Box 19, Folder 208)
    - Naugatuck, Wolcott, Prospect, Middlebury, Beacon Falls, 1933-1939 (Box 20, Folder 209)
    - Litchfield, Goshen, Cornwall, Morris Bethlehem, 1933-1937 (Box 20, Folder 210)
    - Riverton, Colebrook, 1932-1938 (Box 20, Folder 211)
    - Salisbury, Sharon, 1933-1936 (Box 20, Folder 212)
    - Thomaston, Washington, Willimantic, Wilton, 1933-1936 (Box 20, Folder 213)
    - Waterbury, Watertown, 1931-1941 (Box 20, Folder 214)
    - Disarmament meeting, Waterbury, 1931-1933 (Box 20, Folder 215-216)
  - Speeches, Kimball
    - Correspondence concerning, 1930-1941 (Box 20, Folder 217-218)
    - Correspondence re: radio broadcasts, 1935-1939, undated (Box 21, Folder 219)
    - Notes and background material, 1931-1942, undated (Box 21, Folder 220-222)
  - Waterbury, Conn., 1933-1938 (Box 21, Folder 223)
- Additional Material, 1900s-1970s, undated; Accession 1990-M-063; 9.5 linear feet (10 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1990 Feb
  Received from: Mary Eliza Kimball, Elmira Lee Kimball Byron, and Helen Chase Kimball-Brooke, 1990 Mar 15
  - Correspondence, personal, 1906-1940s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, personal, 1940s-1960s, 1971, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Reverend Vincent Donovan and others pertaining to Catholicism (5 folders), 1940s (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Reverend James Fisher, 1955-1960 (Box 2)
  - The Converted Catholic, correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 2)
  - Business correspondence (3 folders), undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence to others: Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Kimball (parents) and Mary Lee Evans Kimball (wife), 1940s (Box 2)
  - American Bar Association, Committee on International Control of Atomic Energy, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - American policy in the Arctic, 1948-1951 (Box 3)
  - Arms Embargo Resolution, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Arms trade (3 folders), 1930s, undated (Box 3)
  - Arms and neutrality legislation, 1935-1937, undated (Box 3)
  - Catholic Association for International Peace, San Francisco Conference, 1945 May (Box 3)
  - Catholicism (5 folders), 1940s, undated (Box 3)
  - Chemical warfare, 1959, 1968-1970, undated (Box 3)
  - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Second Congregational Church, Waterbury
    - Social action committee, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
    - Forum, 1930s (Box 3)
    - Pastoral supply committee, 1930s-1940s (Box 3)
    - Printed material, 1919-1930s (Box 3)
  - Second Congregational Society, Waterbury